[Music]
do
hello everybody welcome to the first
episode of 2022 the first ask abhijit
live episode of 2022 i wish you all a
very happy gregorian new year for those
of you who celebrate it
i hope that you have a very successful
happy prosperous and healthy
new year
so uh as you know this is a
this is a session in which i'm gonna
take questions from the comments
so let us take a very appropriate first
question for this
year okay so this is the first question
bring something new to your channel
and please tell us your new plans for
2022 any books in the making new youtube
channels new documentaries etc
very good question
so it's time to make the announcements
of what's going to change this year so
in the past year i did 72 live streams
ask a budget i took thousands of
questions it was a very unstructured
year i was just taking your questions
and i was answering them all and i was
releasing a lot of short clips
throughout the past six months or so
the first thing that changes this year
is that there will be no more short
clips
that ends right right away
the second thing
is again more of the same i'm gonna do a
hundred i'm planning to uh target a
hundred episodes of the ask a widget
show this year so that's gonna continue
as before
the third thing and this is new
i am planning
to have at least 50 conversations with
guests on this channel right here so
that is something which i have done only
once or twice before on this channel i
interviewed dr subosh and i and i
spoke with uh abhijit ayamitra this year
i'm gonna take it to a whole different
level i'm gonna do at least minimum
50 such conversations with selected
guests
so i am a very curious person i have
lots of interest very diverse interests
so i'm gonna call people from different
backgrounds people who are doing
interesting work interesting people from
different fields
and the objective is to have an
interesting extended conversation with
them i want to learn things from various
people i want you all to gain again
interesting new knowledge and learn new
things from these guests
so in case you all have some suggestions
for me to call some people let me know
in the comments below i will certainly
uh
take all of your suggestions very
seriously i gotta promise that i'll
invite all of them but i will certainly
take it very seriously and invite as
many of them as i can and i also have
some people in mind over the long run
so that is uh something new that's going
to happen on this channel
apart from this i am going to do
50 documentaries on one of my other
channels so i have a couple of other two
three other channels uh that are not
really very active right now
one of these channels is going to see
the release of 50 documentary style
videos starting from the second or third
week of january and it's gonna continue
week week upon week
so there is a thing
now am i going to be
is are there any books in the making yes
it is now time that i should write some
books
so one book that i am going to be
writing this year is i can i would call
it tentatively
the best of azkabajit so over the past
six months i've answered thousands of
questions and many of you have said uh
have asked me for references that you
know where did you get this information
for so i'm gonna take
let's say the best 150 questions
uh answer them in the written form and
provide references
so so i've already answered the
questions you don't need to buy the
books but in case you want uh it in
written form with references you can go
ahead and buy the book whenever it is
released i am planning to do it as fast
as possible next five six months maximum
so the best the best of ask a budget
that's the first book the second book
i'll be working on
is an overview of indian history the
past 70 000 years
right so
it will be an easy to read book a
reasonably fast paced book
easy to read for everybody in which i
will be touching upon
the entire
uh entirety of the past 70 thousand
years of indian history and i'll bring
out many faces of facets of indian
history that most people don't know
about so i will try my best to uh
make it as informative and and put out
as much new information as i can in this
book
so that is the second book and i also
want to write a third book in this year
uh let's the working title i could give
it is uh
astrophysics for everyone so it will
cover uh
it will give in knowledge about the
earth the solar system the galaxy the
universe and everything in between it
will again be an easy to understand book
i think even a 13 year the target which
i have is that even a 13 year old kid
shouldn't be able to understand it it
should not be complicated and
difficult to understand so these are the
things that i want to do this year a
hundred ask a widget episodes at least
50 conversations 50 documentaries three
books
and some other things as well so that is
a
it's not a ton of work it's a mega ton a
giga ton of work that i'm going to be
doing this year so um
so that is the plan it's certainly a
whole lot of work but if you want to
reach the moon you have to aim for the
star so so that's the
philosophy i am
adopting
and let's have a review on december 31
and see how much of this i have
accomplished but i am planning i'm
targeting to accomplish all of this
so that i hope answers this question
okay karan says how to become successful
and rohan says
i know you don't get such questions very
often but since it's the new year
do you have any advice on how one should
set and achieve his or her goals
good questions so like i just said i
have these enormous
goals in front of me for the year 2022.
very ambitious goal so it will require a
lot a lot of hard work from my part from
my side now to become successful and for
goal setting you have to first we have
to first understand the difference
between a goal
and a dream
understand the difference between a goal
a dream is i want to have three books at
the end of the year a dream is i want to
have a hundred ask a budget episodes by
have at least 50 conversations extended
conversations with guests by the end of
this year these are dreams
now to make these dreams reality
you need a plan which is a process
what is a process you wake up in the
morning then you do this this this every
day that's a process this these many
hours for this work this many hours for
this task and so on and the goal that
you should have
is to follow the process faithfully
every day so the process is the goal and
your big what you call goals are your
dreams it is the process that converts
those dreams into reality if you work
hard day in and day out and the thing is
when you make a process and you start
implementing it you will need to find
the need to tweak the process because
once you start walking the walking the
talk
then then you will realize that maybe
the process isn't very efficient so
after a few days you will realize you
will have to change some parts of the
process after a couple of weeks you will
have to change something else after a
month or two months once you have made
lots of small tweaks that's when the
process will work as a well-oiled
machine
so that is the goal you must have
to make a good process keep improving it
and make the process the machine that
takes you towards your dreams so the
process
itself
has to be the goal that's how you become
successful and that's how you set and
achieve
goals which are actually dreams
so that's what i can say in brief about
this
okay harsh says can we say that the
british occupation of india was also
because of the mughals
as farook sierra gave the diwani rights
of bengal to the east india company the
most wealthy province of
india
that's a very interesting question i am
sure none of you most of you have not
heard of this individual called farooq
cr he was one of the later turkic
kings
of of
a small portion of northern india
and so to explain what really happened
let me
show you a very interesting article let
me share that article with you
so that is the best way that in which i
can explain it because this article uh
brings this entire story out
very well so let me share my screen with
you
one second
okay
so this is an article
by rakesh krishnan simma
the mughal tax break that cost india its
freedom
so exactly 300 let me just read out the
first first few
paragraphs so that you understand in
detail so 300 years ago
approximately the mughal emperor farooq
sierra issued a furman that issu that
allowed the east india company to
conduct duty-free trade mint its own
coins and the right to fortify its
garrisons allowing the english to
establish colonial rule in india with
relative ease
so since the year 1600 the english had
been trying to gain a foothold in india
but they were not able to break the
monopoly of the portuguese and the dutch
so the portuguese and the dutch were far
ahead of the english around the time
most of the early embassies sent by the
english monarch had returned home
empty-handed
150 years after his foundation
the east india company was only a
zamindar a landlord at chennai and
kolkata and a mere trader
at its inland factories
but patience being in english virtue
began to pay dividend and a big one at
that by the 1650s the english had
obtained exemption from road tax in the
provinces of agra avadh and adjoining
areas
from the beginning the sole aim of the
english was to avoid payment of the
usual taxes and tolls that were paid by
everyone else
now in november 1715
an english embassy led by john
sermon
had a stroke of luck when one of its
members william hamilton a physician
managed to relieve the emperor farouk's
year of severe pain in his groin
peter auber courts quotes from reports
of the embassy to kolkata the emperor
celebrated his recovery by a public
darbar 30th november 1715
at which he rewarded hamilton with a
splendid gown
diamond rings a crest with precious
stones gold buttons set with jewels a
miniature gold set of whatever of
medical instruments an elephant a horse
and rupees 5000
however
the english had not come for these small
trinkets
they hung around delhi for two more
years for the real prize
in april in april 1717 the embassy hit
paydirt when when farooq cr
issued three separate firmans
for each of the three presidencies of
kolkata mumbai and chennai other demands
submitted by the embassy were con were
covered
by secret separate directives or
hospital
hokums
when the pharmans reached kolkata in
mumbai the presidents and councils
received it with regal honors and so on
so in return for a paltry payment of
rupees 30 000 per year the furman gave
the english a virtual
blanche the right to export and import
goods in bengal without paying taxes
permission to purchase 38 villages
surrounding the three already held by
the company
the right to keep a garrison that is a
military garrison and to further fortify
kalikata the right to issue the stocks
or passes which would ensure the free
passage of goods under the name of the
company without being checked at custom
houses the right to mint gold and silver
coins which would be honored throughout
the mughal empire their own currency
complete freedom to establish factories
at any place the provinces were to
provide the company with assistance the
company would retain its old privilege
of tax exemption in hyderabad province
no increase in the company's existing
rent at chennai exemption from paying
all customs and dues at surat
and
the company's servants were not
permitted were permitted to trade but
were not covered by the ferments they
were required to pay the same taxes and
indian merchants
etc so this is what this this individual
farooq cr the so-called mughal emperor
did he gave this incredible uh
this incredible largesse to the east
india company he essentially converted
east the east india company from a
trading organization into a political
force
in india
so
to answer the question yes the british
occupation of india
was
to a great uh to to to a great extent
because of this action of the so-called
emperor farooq cr who gave all these
rights to the east india company in
bengal and other
other places
and that's how the hd company was
overnight transformed into a political
force and the military force in india
okay knowledge seeker says how often in
a century or so does bharat get a great
leader by seeing the patterns of history
so let's let's examine the great leaders
of the past
so when we talk about the last great
leader that india had
i can think of the great chatrapati
shivaji maharaj right so he
lived in the 17th century between 1630
and 1680 so that's the last great king
of india he
set the foundation for what would
eventually become the great maratha
empire but it is because of him and the
groundwork that he
did and the framework the political and
military framework that he created that
the maratha empire was able to
essentially reconquer all of india from
the turks so the last great reader
leader is chatrapati shivaji maharaja in
the 17th century before him
we had two great leaders that i can
think of that i consider great
the two great chola emperors raj raj
chola in the
late 10th and early 11th century and his
son the great rajendra chola in the 11th
century so raja raja chola set the
foundation
in southern india in in most
in
in the entirety of the indian peninsula
almost
and his son rajiv chula took that
forward and established an enormous
maritime empire because of his powerful
navy
so these are the two
great emperors of the chola dynasty in
the 10th and 11th century before that
you had lalitha mukta peter the great
kashmiri emperor who conquered great
parts of central asia and much of india
so he lived in the eighth century
before him we had the great
samudra gupta the great emperor samudra
gupta who lived in the fourth century he
conquered enormous parts i mean he had
an enormous empire of his own
before samadhika the last
before him the previous great emperor of
india was the great kanishka kanishka
the great in the second century
a.d
and before kanishka the great you had
people like uh the before him we had the
great emperor chandragupta maurya in the
third in the fourth and third centuries
bce so from this from this list from
this partial list of great emperors of
india kings of india one could say that
you come across a great king or emperor
in india or a great great leader one
would say in india once every 300 to 500
years
once every three to 500 years you get a
great
leader in india
so it's been about
how long has it been since the great
shivaji maharaj died 1680 17 18 19 20.
it's about
350 years it's been
so i think it's high time for us to
great greatly to to get
a great leader of that caliber because
india needs that right now
so india has seen rises and false ups
and downs but the past 1000 years have
been uniformly bad
so it's time for india to discover
a new great leader who can pull india
out of the current mediocrity it is in
and propel india again to the greatness
that is rightfully her own right so
let's see how that goes
okay avinash says how can we define
universe what came first matter or empty
space good question so i would define
universe what is the universe it is all
of space time
and everything that exists within it
which is radiation matter and it also
includes all the physical laws that
govern energy and matter
so that's what i would
use as the definition
of universe that is what the universe is
now what came first matter or empty
space
what came first was space-time and pure
energy so in the very very initial
moments after the big bang
the universe was just energy pure energy
extremely
highly compressed condensed energy into
a very small point so space time and
energy and the the grand unified force
out of which all the other forces have
eventually emerged
so that is what what came first not
matter not empty space space time and
pure energy that's what came first
okay gokul says how did jupiter become a
failed star
so
what is a star a star is a big
mostly spherical
uh
ball
of mostly hydrogen gas that is
undergoing fusion because of the
enormous weight of the gas of the gas so
this gas because of the force of gravity
compresses the insides of the star and
that ignites fusion because of the
enormous forces that are involved in
this so that's how
you have the ignition of fusion inside a
newborn star
and that is what what makes stars shine
and glow and give off
the radiation that we see so that's why
the sun is so bright because there is a
fusion reaction going on inside which is
converting
hydrogen into helium and giving off
various uh
and giving of electromagnetic radiation
in various spectra including the
infrared which is heat and visible light
and other other
other frequencies of light so that is
what a star is now why do some people
call jupiter a failed star a jupiter
jupiter is a gas giant planet it's made
up of gas it's a big ball of gas just
like a star but
so some would characterize it as a
failed star because it has not been able
to ignite fusion within its core because
it is not large enough
so that's why one could
characterize jupiter as a failed star
similarly you could also characterize
saturn as a failed star that too is a
big
ball
of gas mainly i would say
hydrogen with some other impurities
sprinkled in
so a failed star is a big
ball of gas
mainly hydrogen that has not succeeded
in uh
in igniting nuclear fusion within its
core you also have these brown dwarfs
that are like somewhere between
a star and a gas giant so that's another
category
of failed stars
so i think the threshold for a gas giant
becoming a star is about 93 jupiter
masses if i can if i recall correctly
so you need to be way bigger than
jupiter in or you know in order to
become the smallest category of stars
so uh yeah so that's why some people
would call jupiter a failed star
hosmok solanki says we in the we
understand the border dispute between
countries
however within the country then the when
the whole of india is one then why do
some states fight for a region not in
their territory like in the northeastern
states between assam and mizoram then
you have maharashtra and karnataka etc
why is this how is this dispute
different from that between
countries
yeah this is an interesting question you
have
several border disputes between various
states you have the region of belgaum
that is currently in karnataka that
maharashtra also has a claim towards
then
assam in mizoram also there is some some
minor border dispute then you have
nagaland which claims the entirety of
the north east more or less even parts
of burma they call it nagalim or
whatever it is
and so on you know you have these
territorial disputes you also have this
dispute about water
water fairing the kaveri water dispute
has been it's been going on for
for decades i think
so you have so what is the what is the
root cause of all these disputes
the root cause of these disputes
is the way the british divided india
into provinces and which we have
continued as
states in india so the british divided
india into linguistic provinces
a province it was one in which a certain
language was prevalent
so
today that is the indian states and the
indian states are also more or less
divided on linguistic lines
right but then you have the problem that
some states are enormous
and some states are very small take
uttar pradesh it is as big almost as big
i mean as half of europe i would say its
population is almost the same very
similar to the population of the united
united states it's just one state in
india
then you have little states in the
northeast like manipur and mizoram etc
whose population is microscopic compared
to uttar pradesh
right so you have this incredible
disparity in india
and because
states have valuable resources
their politicians want to want to
acquire more resources so in case you
have a linguistic
region which is kind of mixed then both
states would claim it and because if you
have one more district under you you can
extract more resources out of it more
tax more revenue more whatever else that
the politicians do
that's why they want it
and that's why you have these disputes
see the thing is at the lower levels in
india
in the lower levels in politics at state
level not stay maybe state level also
i'm not saying it's everywhere
but there is certainly the presence of
this there is a lot of corruption
there's a lot of corruption in there
at lower levels district level
uh
municipal level
ward level etc
and if you have an extra district in
your hands you get to
extract more
whatever you want to call it i'm not
saying this thing is prevalent all
across india there are places i'm sure
which are not corrupt i hope so
uh i'm sure there are but you know this
this is the kind of thing which you have
and that's why politicians want to grab
more territory and that's why there are
this territorial dispute it's one of the
reasons
so what is the solution to this
what's the solution
the solution is very simple
have smaller states why can't india have
a hundred states all of which have more
or less the same size
now i can hear what people are gonna say
no you're trying to break up over unity
you're gonna you're trying to destroy
our unity what about tamil nadu you want
to break up tamil nadu into 50 into
small pieces what about gujarat you want
to break gujarat into small pieces and
so on i'm not saying we need to break it
up why can't you have five tamil states
or about five gujarati speaking states
or 23 uh
states that are made out of up
you see what the thing is that when you
have smaller states smaller
administrative units then you have far
better administration and far more
accountability of the politicians
towards the people
when a state has a population of 300
million
how will you approach the chief minister
with whatever problem you have
but if you have a state with a
population of just one million the chief
minister is far more approachable and
the officials are far more approachable
so if you have smaller administrative
divisions
then you have better administration you
have more accountability
so that is the way in which
perhaps
india's leaders should take india
towards
it is all about empowering the people
making the state the system more
accountable
and delivering better governance
right
so maybe that is something that
india's
leaders not politicians politicians are
not leaders but the real leaders of
india
maybe it is something they should
consider going forward in the long run
maybe that would empower the people
better it would make india a far better
governed
nation
so there is something that could
possibly be explored maybe in india with
a hundred states all of a reasonably
similar sizes and populations that would
make india a far better governed
nation
so this just a thought
all right
uh is the government spending in the
wrong places like bullet trains and
private trains aren't various yojanas
waste of taxpayers money and as they are
a free medium to earn
for the ones who do not want to work i
don't think any other country has these
types of schemes in the developed
world
you know
in 1945
japan was a nation that was in ruins
japan was smoldering
smoke was emanating from its major urban
centers
every single large city in japan
or even medium city in japan had been
had been bombed to the ground
by the americans
all industries were destroyed
hiroshima and nagasaki were nuked
right japan was
was essentially in ruins the whole
country
and in a few decades
it emerged as the number two economy in
the world as a genuine
bonafide financial superpower
economic superpower
and
what drove
the transformation of japan
it was high technology and investing
this technology in creating the
infrastructure that unifies the nation
and allows people greater mobility
and greater connectivity
so that it it essentially makes
running businesses and industries and
governance and everything like that
far easier and what was behind this
one of the major components in this
was the shinkansen bullet train
the bullet train
connected the whole of japan
and made the country in a way smaller
you could reach any place in a couple of
hours
and they made it affordable as per the
per capita gdp of japan
so that is something that transformed
japan
now we have seen we have witnessed the
rise of china in the past two decades
one of the factors
that has
propelled this rise of china is the
chinese bullet train network
china has today they have built over the
past two decades the greatest the
largest bullet trade network in the
world
high speed trains
and because of this
people are able to travel all across
china very quickly
it's it's enabled people to to uh
commute from from the residence to a far
off place to a place of work and come
back in the night that sort of thing
so if you invest in this sort of
connectivity this sort of infrastructure
it
pays back
hundreds of times you know the kind of
investment you made in the long run
it's like
why do we need rockets why do we need
israel
what does it do for the common man and
woman and child
it pays you back i mean the satellite
capabilities that we have they
empower indians so much we don't even
understand the impact of that technology
our day-to-day life would not be
possible without the technology
similarly bullet trains are needed india
has a horribly outdated
railway system
you want to go somewhere by train you
have to book a ticket one month in
advance if the website allows you to
book there's always a waiting list and
god knows what
in a civilized developed country
let's say you're sitting in in madurai
southern india
let's say you wake up this morning
or tomorrow morning and you decide for
whatever reason i need to go to guwahati
in a civilized country you should be
able to just go to the station purchase
a ticket on the spot sit down and train
in the next half an hour and be in
guwahati within six to eight hours
that is what a developed civilized
country looks like today you have these
extremely
slow trains compared to bullet train
standards
that you can't even walk to a station
and book a ticket right away and get
into a train you have to book a month in
advance or god knows what how long that
waiting list waiting time is
so india is still in the in the almost
in the colonial era
most of the rail network that india has
was built by the british for their
extraction purposes for the purpose of
blundering india india has not added
much to it it is high time india creates
its own
21st century
bullet train
infrastructure
it doesn't necessarily have to be bullet
trains they need to be high speed trains
and there must there we need to have the
kind of infrastructure where you can
just walk into a station
on whenever needed buy a ticket purchase
a ticket and be on a train within the
next 30 to 60 minutes and go wherever
you need to go there should be no
waiting list and all that nonsense
that's what a civilized developed
country
looks like
so that's what india needs
so i don't think it's it's wrong
spending there are certain yojanas that
you speak about that are a complete
waste of money i do not disagree with
that but the bullet train
infrastructure other infrastructure that
india is building it is an investment
for the future it is your children
children and your grandchildren who will
benefit from that
but various uh
employment generation schemes and
whatever else that is a waste of money
but that is because of political
compulsions
in india certain things the way the
indian political system works you have
to throw money
lots of
taxpayer money at
various sections of society in order to
keep getting those votes that's just how
it is it's what
it's what the politicians created
in the 1950s 60s 70s onwards you know
and that's what that's the
and we are reaping the the rewards
of that system that horrible system so i
i hope in the next
in the coming decades all this will
change
leadership
that's what we need
okay ashi says
you said gandhi was a british agent but
khan abdul gafar khan was a great
freedom fighter
but khan abdul gafar khan also used
non-violent resistance to fight against
the british and abdul gafar khan was
known as the frontier gandhi because he
followed the ideals of mahatma gandhi
my dear friend ashishdar let me ask you
something
i agree
khan abdullah khan was a great freedom
fighter i agree
i agree that he used non-violent
resistance to fight the british i agree
i agree that he was called the frontier
gandhi because he followed the ideals of
mahatma gandhi i agree
now please tell me something
did khan abdul gafar khan
succeed
in achieving his objective
of a unified
india
what was his objective his objective was
a unified
india a unified subcontinent
he did not want partition he opposed
partition he wanted a peaceful united
india did he succeed in his objective
he failed
now please tell me why did he fail
he failed because of the methods he
adopted
he adopted non-viral resistance
he adopted gandhi's ideals what happened
what was the outcome he failed
end of story
okay
if gandhi was a british agent why did
churchill hate him so much
i would not agree
that winston churchill hated gandhi
we know what churchill said about gandhi
right
what do those pronouncements
actually tell us
they tell us that winston churchill
had contempt
for mohandas gandhi he was contemptuous
towards gandhi
he had no respect towards gandhi hating
somebody
and being contemptuous and disrespectful
is two different things
you can hate somebody but respect them
do you know that
the thing is churchill did not respect
gandhi
he was contemptuous towards gandhi it is
not hatred it is a lack of respect that
he consistently demonstrated towards
gandhi now i want you to ask yourselves
why churchill was unable to find any
respect in his heart for mohandas gandhi
please ask yourselves
bhakta says your face looks like the
former president of pakistan yaya khan
patan
let's let's take a look at yahya khan
patan shall we
hang in there let me share my screen
yahya khan
it was a pashtun yes
what they look like
this is what this guy looks like look
like
check out those eyebrows guys
check out the eyebrows wow
i certainly don't have that sort of
eyebrows
incredible eyebrows
so this is what it looked like do i look
like this
maybe i may look like that when i'm 70
years old or something there he is with
richard nixon
yahya khan
anyhow so
yeah there he is with the american
president richard nixon another crook
so the thing is see that the thing is
this
i don't know if i look like him or not
but the thing is that indians and
pashtuns the people of afghanistan are
the same people we have the same origins
in a previous episode i've actually
demonstrated that with genetic evidence
from various research papers that
conclusively show that the patans and
pashtuns
have the same genetics the same origins
as the rest of the indian population
so if i look like somebody who has
pursued ethnicity or somebody else
it's no surprise it's no surprise we are
the same people
afghanistan is gandhar that's part of
india that's historically been part of
india for thousands of years from the
mahabharata
from the vedic days and even before that
so there's no surprise if the people of
india and the pashtun people look
similar because we are the same people
we have the same ancestry
okay um
the question is by ahmad illahi i am
from pakistan i want to know your
opinion about india pakistan
confederation which we can call a union
like the european union is it possible
so let's understand what the eu is the
european union it's a political union of
a number of countries in europe
and it is based upon certain shared
values shared principles and share
shared objectives
so there is a great deal of political
concerns between these between the the
nations that make up the european union
they are bound by
they have agreed to follow the same laws
and uh
allow
free access
to each other's territory for for the
citizens and so on and so forth so there
is a great deal of commonality between
them and they have they have agreed
willingly
to uh
to adhere to certain rules principles
laws and all that
so there is political unity there right
now
let's take india and pakistan do we have
that sort of political concerns
cultural concerns do we have that
religious concerns do we have that
i have absolutely nothing against the
people of pakistan i
i have said this many times whether we
are the same people we have the same
roots the same past same ancestry and
all that but india and pakistan are very
different countries today very very very
different countries pakistan is a
dictatorship run by
by the pakistani army it is now
essentially a vasal of china
it sees india as the mortal enemy it's
its highest ambition is to conquer india
someday and destroy whatever is left of
indian culture in india
these are undeniable facts
so can we have a political union unity
between india and pakistan given these
circumstances it's not possible today
it's not possible at all today
i would like
very much
to see the indian subcontinent unite
again
in the future
but this has to be a long-term project
this has to be a long-term project it is
not going to happen
for let's say the next 100 years at
least
it's not going to happen for at least
the next 100 years because of the
inherent
deep-rooted
cultural religious differences the
different
mindsets the different worldviews
you simply can't have
political unity or some kind of
confederation because in any
confederation you need open borders you
need free flow of people
it is not
in india's interests to allow free flow
of people from pakistan at any time in
the near future or even the
medium-term future
it's just not in india's interests
and therefore
good as this suggestion is as good as it
is
i mean
it's it's it's not it's not practical
as of now and it's not going to be
practical in the next 50 to 100 years in
the long run i would like to see india
india i mean the indian subcontinent
reunite
again
and reclaim its past glory and and
see it's see a
proper revival of its
original
cult
is why does the taliban not recognize
the durand line
so i may have spoken about this in the
past i have several episodes on
afghanistan
but let's go into it once again
because i'm sure there are lots of new
viewers who may not have seen that so
let's talk about it so if you look at
the past history of afghanistan of
gandha it was part of india it was a it
was a hindu buddhist
uh
part of india
right but then you had the turkic
invasions and you had this change of
culture forcible obviously all the
monuments everything was destroyed all
the temples stupas everything is in
ruins now and there was the entire
change in culture that was engineered by
the turks in afghanistan
so
afghanistan is essentially the original
kashmir that's what happened there
now so the people of afghanistan
eventually became culturally different
and then you had these invasions of
india emanating from afghanistan in the
past 1000 years
right
now in the 18th century you had this
individual called ahmad shah abdali
nowadays they call him ahmad durrani
he launched eight invasions into india
with the objective of plundering
the land
in the 18th century
right it caused a great amount of death
and destruction in india a lot of
plunder was taken out of india
by this individual
this was in the
18th century
then what happened is that you had this
uh you had this new political entity
that emerged in northern india which was
the kingdom
of maharaja ranjit singh
who lived in the late 18th and first
half of the 19th century
right so he
unified the various sikh factions
and
created the sikh kingdom or well it's
called the sick empire though even
though it was not very large it's called
the sick empire
so he was one of the great kings
and what he did was that he punished the
afghans for all the
depredations they had done in india all
the plunder all the atrocities the the
massacres etc he punished the afghans
for that
he
went to war with the afghans
he conquered a great deal of
of afghan territory
right
and he created a very large
uh kingdom or empire in northern india
which included
which included significant portions of
what is called pashtun islam so lots of
pashtun territory he captured that and
he incorporated that into his kingdom it
came under his political dominion
so the sikh empire included large parts
significant portions of pashtun
dominated pashtun majority territory
now maharaja singh died in 1839 within a
decade the sick empire crumbled
right and the british took over
now what the british did was that they
used
the border of the sikh empire as their
own border with afghanistan essentially
the border between british india and
afghanistan so that became the
foundation of the durand line the durand
line was delineated in 1893
it was drawn by the british and it was
essentially the border of the sikh
empire which maharaja singh had
conquered
it included parts of pashtun dominated
territory
so
that was then reconfirmed in
the anglo-afghan treaty of 1919 in which
the afghan kingdom the king of
afghanistan amir afghanistan he agreed
with the british in this treaty to treat
this duran line as the boundary between
afghanistan which was a sovereign
independent nation and british india
so that is the history of the durand
line which is essentially the border of
the sikh empire
now in 1947 pakistan partitioned from
india it became a separate nation
and
the durant line was then used as the
boundary between pakistan and
afghanistan
but the people of afghanistan the
pashtuns they have this historical
grudge that this is our territory that
you have taken over
even though our king agreed in this
treaty with the british but now the
british are gone
the british are gone so why should we
now recognize
this uncrazy line on the map
as
our boundary
we have our people living on the other
side in pakistan's khyber pathua and
north-west frontal province etc
right
so
they do not recognize the durant line as
the legitimate boundary between pakistan
and afghanistan
and that is the reason why the taliban
which essentially are a pashtun
nationalist force
they do not recognize the durant line as
the legitimate boundary between pakistan
afghanistan there is a big territorial
dispute between pakistan and afghanistan
which the taliban has inherited and it
is going to be fun and games to watch
how it plays out over the next
three to five years
because the taliban do not recognize
that as the boundary between afghanistan
and pakistan and they have a territorial
claim
on pakistan so right now the pakistanis
have engineered a certain kind of
leadership in the taliban they have put
their own people
in leadership positions in the taliban
how long will it last in this terrorist
organization things will change
things are going to change wait and
watch
and then
we're going to have some
fireworks
over there
so
it's a matter of time nothing more
okay we see that shivaji that chatrapati
shivaji is the father of the indian navy
but ships and boats were there even
before him also so why do we call him as
the father of the indian navy so you're
absolutely right uh the thing is that uh
chitrapathi shivaji
was in the maratha empire as a whole
where was the last
sovereign indian
political entity that had its own navy
and it had a very powerful navy
very agile very lean and very powerful
very efficient very effective
naval force led by the great kanoji
angry i believe
right and it defeated the portuguese and
the british in many battles and all that
so yes that was the last
independent sovereign indian navy that
we had before the british indian navy
came into force india has always been a
maritime nation when that individual uh
what's his name vasco da gama he went
around the cape of good hope
he had the biggest ship that the
portuguese were able to build and he saw
indian ships there were like three four
times the size of his trip
so that tells you the great history of
indian shipbuilding india was the
greatest ship building nation on the
surface of the planet for
most
of known history and
even before that
so if you talk about the great cholas
the chula empire they had a powerful
really powerful navy which they used to
conquer the entirety of southeast asia
they invaded southeast asia by putting
uh infantry soldiers etc on big naval
ships
and they were able to go all the way
across the bay of bengal go into across
the malacca strait get into the
so-called
south china which is actually the champa
sea and conquer all these territories
there
that's how powerful their navy was so
clearly there wasn't there were powerful
naval forces before the marathas and
even if you talk about uh samadhi gupta
the great
the great emperor samudra gupta he also
had a powerful navy which he used
to conquer
much of if not most of southern india
and bring it under his political
dominion so he also used naval force
and we have rep i mean
we had the great uh
the great kingdoms in kalinga which used
navy which had which had powerful naval
capabilities we know that i have spoken
about this in the in a previous episode
you will you can see the short clip is
which is there in my on this channel and
so on and even in the vedas there are
mentions
of ships with a hundred ores
that is a pretty big ship right and if
you go to southeast asia cambodia et
cetera where you have kalinga influence
you will see depictions of great ancient
indian ships
uh in those shaivite hindu kingdoms
right
so that's what you had that is the great
history of indian shipbuilding and
indian
naval
power which which your his with your
history textbooks and your teachers do
not want you to know about
so
these are the facts so india has always
been a great great maritime
nation and civilization
okay what is the bare minimum
requirement
audrey asks what is the bare minimum
of number of warships and submarines
that uh the indian navy should have
to counter china and other neighbors
also number of planes the iaf needs
okay let us go to the map
to understand how to approach this
question
so this is the indian ocean region as
you can see india dominates the indian
ocean region india is in the in this
spectacularly god gifted position
geographically in the indian ocean
region
right so india is has been given this
gift by the gods of being able to
dominate this region if it's so vicious
so how many naval ships do you need
to
what's the question
to counter china and other neighbors so
if you look at
the indian ocean region if you can see
my mouse pointer this is
this region that india calls its
strategic backyard it is approximately i
would say 10 million
square kilometers or more than that
right
that is a big big piece of naval real
estate 10 million square kilometers at
least
so that is what india needs to dominate
in order to counter china and other
neighbors
so how many warships do you think we
need to have
patrolling this region at any given
point in time
i would say at least a hundred warships
at any given point in time because to
dominate a region
you need a visible
presence there at all times constant
patrolling constant presence you should
be seen to be there yes there are indian
ships everywhere that's what you need to
have
so to patrol
this
region of 10 million square kilometers
you would need to have constant
deployment of at least 100 warships
which would include destroyers cruisers
frigates corvettes etc
and
you would also need at least 30
submarines to be deployed in this in
this huge region at any given point in
time constantly only then can you
dominate this region and consider it to
be your strategic backyard
now there's this
this uh
there is a very hard fact in the navy
which most people don't know about
that
for every three ships you have
only one is actively deployed at any
time
because one ship will be
at port
undergoing repairs refueling
renovation
one ship will be either coming
to the port or going towards this
destination and one will be actively
deployed so for every three ships for
every three naval assets you have only
one will be typically deployed at any
given point in time so if india needs at
least
100 warships to be deployed at any given
point in time india actually needs to
build at least 300
warships
that's what india needs
if you want at least 30 submarines to be
deployed at any given point in time you
must have at least 90 submarines
in your
navy
so that is what india needs to do india
is far far far away from that right now
india's naval strength is about 120 130
i'm not sure the exact numbers but many
of those assets are not warships
there are tankers there are other things
in all and so on so forth
so india needs to invest significant
funds into building
a modern 21st century navy with the
numbers that we just mentioned we need
destroyers we need cruisers frigates
corvettes missile boats are also a very
useful
addition to your navy and they are quite
cheap actually if you know how to build
them
and submarines we need the
various kinds of submarines including
nuclear submarines which we are building
but we are still far from the numbers
that we need so that is the kind of
situation that we would like to see
in and if we get those numbers in our
kitty
then the chinese will not be able to
interfere in our strategic backyard
now when it comes to the iaf number of
planes we need they say we need 32 33 34
uh squadrons of planes a squadron is
typically roughly 20 planes 22
right
but i would say the more the better we
don't need the latest most high-tech
planes
we can the thing is this
quantity has a quality of its own if you
look at the chinese air force they have
large numbers many of those planes that
they have are very antiquated planes but
they still use them
let's say you have a plane of the of the
caliber of a mig-21 which is a 1960s
plane but what if you have a thousand of
those
what if you have a thousand of those
planes of the caliber of a mig-21 they
will overwhelm any
air force
from our neighborhood
so we need quantity we need quality we
are developing high quality aircraft
with the lca pages mark 1a is
soon to be uh
the mass production will start in a
couple of years i think then you have
the medium weight fighter
we have the twin engine deck bait deck
based fighter and then we have the amca
the advanced
uh combat aircraft which will be a fifth
generation stealth aircraft so all those
are being developed
but what we can do in the interim is to
churn out lots of these these tejas mark
1a aircraft you know we need numbers we
need quality quality as well so i would
say india needs at least at least
500 ford fighter aircraft and maybe we
can also invest in heavy duty bombers
you know
maybe acquire some from russia or build
our own
so this is something that needs to
happen in the next 10 20 years maximum
in order to for india to become
immune to the threats from its
neighborhood
okay dominic says israel recently
carried out an airstrike on the latakia
port in syria
but the s-400s were not able to take
down the israeli fighter jets
as at the same time a russian russian
plane was in the air
is it the same with every s400 system in
other countries too
no it is not the same
the s 400 is not a low quality inferior
system
it is the most dangerous
air defense system
that currently exists now we have the
s500 which is even better right here and
even the s550 is being developed but
among the major air systems that we have
the s 400 is one of the best in its
class it's far superior to the american
system the israeli system etc
so
and it has this
friend or foe identification also
inbuilt into it which ensures that even
in a contested airspace when you have
two kinds of fighter aircraft from two
opposing forces engaged in air combat it
will not shoot down your aircraft it
will only target the enemy aircraft so
it has all those capabilities
so the question is
when the israelis just a few days ago
carried out at least
one or two airstrikes on the latakia
port in syria
why was no action taken why was the s
400 there
unable to take out the israeli planes
because there is an s-400 system
deployed nearby
it's a russian system the russians are
operating it because the russians have
geopolitical interests in syria
see here's the situation
there was this attempt about 10 years
ago to bring down the syrian president
bashar al-assad
it was a western attempt to do that now
vladimir putin and russia intervened in
this and they succeeded in ensuring that
the syrian government is not overthrown
today the bashar al-assad is quite
secure in syria
thanks to the russian
to russian help
and the russians are operating various
military
bases etc in syria
they have this s-400 system
near the latakia port
where they also have some naval assets
from time to time
right
and then the israelis did this they
bombed the port
and there was no response from the s-400
why is this
it is because
the russians chose
not to bring down the israeli planes
whether there was a russian plane in the
air at the time or not is immaterial the
s-400 will not bring out bring down a
russian plane
the russians chose not to stop the
israelis and not to target their planes
they allowed the israelis
to
carry out this airstrike or airstrikes
on the latakia port why is that
they are on the side of the syrians
right they are supporting bashar
al-assad then why did they allow the
israelis to take to carry out an
airstrike
that is the question
see here's the thing
even iran
has an interest in syria
the iranians are also trying to play
geopolitical games in syria
they want to use parts of syria as their
strategic backyard
right
and the russians
do not want that
now it is quite possible that the
that the uh
iranians
had sent some shipments
to latakia port which included weapons
ammunition etc because when this
airstrike happened that consignment
which was targeted it burned for more
than a day
and there were explosions and all that
so clearly there was some ammunitions
and weaponry in there
maybe it came from iran
and maybe the russians don't want
any iranian
presence or hand in syria they want
syria all to themselves
right so maybe that's why they allowed
the israelis to target the iranian
shipment
in this port
so you know we don't have definitive
answers
but we know what's happening
and based on our knowledge of what's
happening we can kind of reconstruct
probable scenarios
of why the s 400 was not activated
it is
an extremely extraordinarily
capable system
it could have
certainly
taken down the israeli planes
but the russians chose not to
okay
i want to ask you i am currently
pursuing aerospace engineering in an iit
people say that for you to have a good
career in this field you have to move
out of india to work but i want to stay
in india and work in organizations like
isro drdo etc and help my country in
some way please guide me
you know first of all congratulations on
pursuing this aerospace engineering in
an iit that's a great it's a very good
accomplishment in itself
now your aim is to help india in some
way and
you want to do that by working in isro
or drdo or one of these major
organizations
so you know when you are young when
you're a student and you are planning a
career you need to have your main goal
main objective which you can call plan a
then you should also have plan b plan c
and plan d
so plan a for you clearly is that you
want to
work in isro or drdo
so make that your primary objective so
to to get a job in isro or drdo i think
you will need to get exceptionally high
marks high grades
in your iit course work
and if you are an outstanding student
you should
have a very good chance of
getting into is or drdo when you apply
as long as applications are open so that
should be your primary objective plan a
but that should not be your only plan if
it fails then what do you do you should
also have plan b plan c plan d so plan b
plan c plan d you need to figure out
what that is for you
there is no harm
if this plan a doesn't work there is no
harm that in in trying to go abroad if
you have good marks excellent grades
then you will be
you'll be able to
work
abroad you can do that for five years
ten years maybe gain some expertise gain
some experience gain new skills
and then maybe you can come back to isro
or drdo so what i'm saying is that it's
a very good thing that you want to work
in isro drdo or whatever else
you should make that your primary
objective and
invest all your time all your energy all
your efforts into succeeding in that but
also have plan b plan c and plan d
ready and well thought out in case plan
a doesn't work because you know life
has all kinds of uncertainties no matter
how good you are sometimes think things
may not work your way so always ensure
that you have backup plans that's what i
would say
but i would
like to wish you the best i hope that
you succeed in this objective of working
in isro or drdo i wish you the best
okay i don't want to reveal my name says
i am a student of 17 to 19 age i feel i
am not free i am constantly under the
control of my parents
i want to break free from all mental
hurdles pressures the ruling attitude of
my parents
and this continuous feeling of
humiliation
but then comes the need of money and the
basic necessities and i feel and i feel
bogged down
and i feel that i can't do anything and
i have to face it am i immersed in my
problem so i'm not able to understand
how could i be free
how can i make my environment and
everyone very good and very sweet for me
so you know what
your parents are usually your best
friends
the overwhelming majority of parents
want their children to succeed and they
do everything they can to support their
children
and help them succeed
in the best possible way
now you know
there are good people there are bad
people in the world and similarly in
some rare cases you may some people may
have bad parents
that that possibility is always there in
some rare cases your parents may not be
very good for you their attitudes may be
stifling or maybe they are too
controlling or maybe they want you to go
in a certain direction which you don't
want to go in it
these
these things happen yes it all depends
on what cards the gods have dealt you
sometimes you get unlucky and
you face this sort of situation
so
the thing is you have
stated the problem that you are facing
and in the statement in the definition
of the problem you also given the
solution
so you are right now 17 19 you are a
student in a good organization in a good
institution that is very good
the problem you are facing the real
problem you're facing is the need of
money and basic necessities right
so that is also the solution
what you need to do is
right now focus on your studies
do very well in your studies get good
grades
get yourself a good job after that and
that ends the problem which is the need
of money which ties you
to uh the whims and fancies of your
parents
so in case your parents are well too
controlling and humiliating you or
whatever like you say
then what you need to do is invest the
next three to five years in getting a
stable
good job which will eliminate
any problem of money that you have and
once you have the money
to live your life on your own terms then
well you will not have that problem
anymore
so your the problem that you've stated
it contains the solution in itself
so that's what i can say
you need to become financially
independent
and then you will be able to go in
whatever direction you like
all the best
animal says
in the flair of leadership is thing
shopping
the greatest of all time especially of
the 20th
century
well then shopping is clearly one of the
greats of the 20th century so
there are a number of people in the 20th
century who can be considered to be
great leaders right he's not the only
one
among the great leaders i can think of i
can give names such as mustafa kamala
tatark of turkey
who brought who essentially created
the modern nation of turkey he
he created the modern nation of turkey
out of the ruins
of the ottoman empire
turkey was at the time under foreign
occupation he led the turkish war of
independence and he created this this
independent united secular nation of
turkey he is called
which means the father of the turks so
he's one of the greats of the 20th
century then you have people like dwight
eisenhower who fought as a soldier as a
major general in the second world war
as president he created nato so he had a
huge impact on the world
and it's his impact still continues
today
when you have whether you like it or not
you have joseph stalin
who defeated hitler
and
and laid the foundations of the great uh
soviet union you know
then you have lee kuan yew who
transformed singapore from a third world
nation to a very very prosperous first
world nation in just 20 years then you
have people like mao setong
well you may not like him but he clearly
created the modern nation of china
under the chinese communist party he
established the chinese communist party
is the undisputed power in china
then you have people like gang shopping
then chopping essentially transformed
china from the days from the
agrarian
poverty stricken days of mao zedong into
and he transformed it into a
he he
he set in process
he set in motion the process of
converting china
into a modern
uh developed
nation so what you see in china today
the transformation that we've seen over
the past two decades it owes its genesis
it's its roots
to the uh
work
of then shopping
and what ding shopping did was he tried
to emulate
the actions of lee kuan yew so there was
a great deal of learning
in china
from the policies of leak 1u
which were implemented in singapore
and then you have somebody like ronald
reagan also that i can think of who is
maybe the last great american president
so these are some of the people who are
the greats of the 20th century
they have in in many ways
shaped the world that we live in today
is then shopping the greatest of all
time of the 20th century he's one of the
greats i would not call him the one
person who is head and shoulders above
everybody else but he's clearly
one of the greats
okay
kayan dhotivala says greetings from the
partners of bombay greetings greetings
sir
why are the finns and the russians not
considered european on my visit to
norway i was told that only blown blonde
haired
and blue eyed individuals are considered
true europeans
and any european with swarthy features
like dark hair or dark eyes
is said to have some sort of foreign
admixture
that's why they believe that spaniards
and greeks look different from swedes as
they are very close to north africa and
have swardy features
you know
the definition of a european is somebody
who lives in europe
so europe is the western part of eurasia
the boundary is typically the caucasus
mountain region
right
so anybody who lives west of that
is by definition european
now the definition that you are
referring to that you have heard from
some people is a very racist definition
of europeans that only people with
blonde hair and blue eyes are europeans
what nonsense
there are people in the celtic regions
of europe the western europe
who many of whom have have red hair
are they not europeans
if you go to ireland scotland there are
lots of people with red hair
are they also i mean are they no longer
europeans because of the color of their
hair the greeks
i mean greece the greek civilization is
considered to be the foundation of
western civilization
most greeks have light brown skin and
dark hair and dark eyes
so you know this definition doesn't
really hold some racist people
like like the nazis for instance they
would have
held such
such ideas
such ideas were in currency during the
nazi age and all that but uh
i don't this is a mainstream view at all
if some people hold such views those are
very regressive and very racist views so
they are being racist towards their
fellow europeans based on their features
these swarthy features so if you have
skin light brown skin then you are no
longer european that way i mean so
that's a very racist attitude to have i
suppose some people in europe may have
that
but if that is to be held as true then
only
a small portion of europe would actually
count as europe which is nonsense
so you know that's what i can say about
this it's a very racist
attitude to have if someone said this
you know
ashish says is china a dharmic country
because it is a buddhist country
so china does have the largest buddhist
population of any nation in the world
more than 200 million
practicing buddhists in china
but china is not about this country
china is officially a communist country
a socialist country
the official doctrine is atheism that's
the official doctrine of the chinese
communist party
right
china is officially an atheist country
nowadays they tolerate the practice of
buddhism
by a significant portion of the
population which is like
one-sixth or one-seventh of their
population
but the overwhelming majority of chinese
they profess atheism
and the official doctrine policy is
atheism therefore china is not a
buddhist country and therefore china is
not a dharmic country a country
can be considered to be dharmic if its
official policies are dharmic policies
the communist party's policies are the
opposite
of dharmic policies
and therefore china cannot be considered
to be a dharmic country india cannot be
considered to be a dharmic country
india is officially a secular country
india is one of the most hinduphobic
countries in the world
india itself is not a dharmic country
sri lanka can be considered to be a
dharmic country
because its official
state religion so to say is buddhism it
is enshrined in the constitution of sri
lanka so sri lanka is a dharmic country
yes
nepal was a dharmic country when it was
a hindu monarchy
that was
destroyed
by the indian government's interference
so today nepal itself is not a dharmic
country you could
say that
thailand is a dharmic country
because it is i think officially or
or quasi officially about this country
and so on
so the answer in short is china is not a
dharmic country by any means whatsoever
sujai says where today's kerala in
madagascar geographically connected
millions of years ago
and yes and if yes in what ways are they
similar to each other today
uh nice question let's go to the map
okay
so the indian subcontinent
about 100 million years ago
was part of the continent of africa
and madagascar was also attached to the
indian continent so if you see the map
here if you can see madagascar
if you can look upon madagascar as a
piece in a jigsaw puzzle you can see
that it will fit into the into the
eastern coast of africa the shape is
very similar and if you see the shape of
madagascar it can also fit in the
western coast of india
the northern tip of madagascar could
easily fit into the
into the
this region
the khambhat region
the gulf of kambaat region of india
so you can see these free these pieces
of geography they fit together so what
happened is that about 90 million or so
years ago because of tectonic activity
the indian subcontinent detached from
africa
and over
tens of millions of years it traveled
across the indian ocean
and it eventually slammed into eurasia
and that collision is still continuing
in this collision has caused the
emergence of the great himalayan
mountain range
right
so it's not just kerala it's the
entirety of western india which was once
attached to madagascar
so in what way what similarities do you
see there
let me see the question again
the question is in what ways are the
similar to each other i think if you
would do soil composition tests etc
you would find similarities between the
soil of madagascar and the soil of the
western
coast
the western coastal region of india
maharashtra karnataka
kerala even gujarat you will find
similarities in the soil composition and
the kind of geology that you have
of course while india was floating in
the indian ocean it passed over the
reunion hotspot
and that gave rise to the enormous
volcanic activity of the deccan traps so
that kind of changed the geological
geomorphological
characteristics of the deccan region but
you will still find some similarities
between the western coastal regions of
india and madagascar if you do
geological tests and soil composition
tests
and you may even find similar fossils
from more than 100 years ago 100 million
years ago in these two regions
so that's what one can say about this
okay arpan says what are your views on
the new nalanda university
has the project already failed as the
chinese have already beat us in it
by starting their own institution if
they can do
if they can we can do a comeback
and so on since excluding are they
flawed by excluding sanskrit from the
curriculum okay so i think this
university the new nalanda university
let's let's take a look at
what we have
let me share my screen and let's do a
google search
so nalanda university new nalanda
what do we have what does google search
tell us
along the university okay so you have
nalanda university here
and yeah it says in 1st september 2014
so the commencement of the first
academic year
of the modern nalanda university with 15
students
let's look at what wikipedia has to say
once again disclaimer wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information but let's
just take a look at it for the sake of
simplicity and brevity
so
post-independence mahavihara doesn't
look like there's much
much information here
okay this is the new naland university
it was established in 2014
the first chance seller of the
university
was the so-called nobel laureate amartya
sen not so called he was certainly a
nobel laureate and this individual
who is an ultra marxist
was made the first chancellor of this
university
right and this modern nalanda university
it offers master's degrees
and it offers phd courses
right
under
the modern indian education system which
is actually a continuation of the 19th
century colonial education system so the
new university they have created they
have given it the name of nalanda
they appointed a marxist as the
first
chancellor of the university and they
are offering courses according to the
colonial british education system
so what's the point of having this
university which is just another
mediocre indian university run by
marxists what is the point
of calling it nalanda
if you want to name a new institution
nalanda
it should
it should be run according to the
principles of the original
nalanda university
it should not be run by marxists and it
should offer education in the same
format
as or a similar format maybe a 21st
century
version of the original format of the
original naland university
so none of that has happened and
therefore yes that institution has
failed it's a failure calling it with a
certain title is not going to make it
great
what makes an institution great is the
quality of the people who run the
institution
and when you have somebody like amartya
sen running a university
it's failed and doomed from the start i
don't know who is the current
vice chancellor it will be somebody
pulled out of the depths of the
mediocrity of any of the modern indian
education system and therefore it's it's
it's a useless and pointless university
they should not
name it nalanda it's an insult to the
original university
gokul says in ancient india how were
people
who had done crimes punished
you see ancient india is thousands of
years
and over thousands of years you have
differences in in the way that the way
things are done
so let's say you're talking about the
mauryan era for instance during the time
of chandragupta maurya and ashoka
at that time the the punishments were
given according to the principles of
vishnu gupta china quarterly in
principle principles
so you had harsh punishments for bad
crimes if you if somebody committed
murder they would be given the death
sentence
but they were given i think a person
sentenced to death was given three days
to meet their family and say their final
goodbye so it was quite compassionate in
that manner but justice was sweet swift
and justice was often
harsh
right
now when you go to the gupta era
during the time of kumara gupta gupta
etc
or
or what's his name etc so at that time
the the i think who was the chinese
traveler fahyan was it the yeah this guy
fighting i think came to india he
traveled extensively around india in the
gupta era
and he noticed he wrote
that
uh the punishments were very
very uh
very
modest very gentle
uh the death penalty was unheard of and
there was very little crime in india
so that's how it was during the gupta
era very uh
very
very generous or very gentle punishments
very mild punishments
and crime itself was very less so it all
depends on how efficiently you run the
state
how efficient your governance is if you
are really efficient and if you are very
swift in dealing out punishments then
most likely you don't have to give very
harsh punishments
so it depends from time to time
in certain eras you had harder harsher
punishments in certain eras you had very
gentle punishments very mild punishments
so
that's
the kind of comparison i can offer you
i'm sure you can do more research and
find more details about
various other eras of indian history
and how things were done in those times
ishwar says
the philippines are going to buy brahmos
missiles from india what will be the
impact on china
and secondly the pakistanis are going to
buy j-10c
fighter jets from china we know the
rafale is better but
how is the j-10c compared to the f-16
with the pakistanis already used
okay i also heard
the news of the filipinos
they are on the verge of a deal with the
indian government which will
enable them to acquire the brahmos
supersonic cruise missile
so that's a good thing for the filipinos
it will give them
it will give them a great deal of
deterrence against the chinese but you
know what it all depends on how you use
the weapons that you have at your
disposal
you may have the best weapons but if
your politicians are weak need
then your weapons are of no use
so
it depends on how the filipinos choose
to deploy and use this missile system
assuming that the sale
is
is done
so i think the filipino president
duterte has an ambivalent kind of
relationship with china
he is a kind of strong man kind of kind
of personality
and
he has at times shown an inclination to
uh
to be willing to talk with china and
have some sort of have good relations
but he also has um he is also a filipino
nationalist so he wants to make the
philippines a strong power in the region
very strong regional power so it all
depends on how it is used but it will
certainly give the philippines
an amount of deterrence and leverage
against china because the chinese are
claiming parts of the philippines also
the parts of filipino territorial waters
as part of their nine dash line and all
that so it will give the filipinos a
significant amount of leverage
now the the pakistani deal to buy j-10c
fighter planes from china
there also is a recent development now
we know that the rafale jet is far far
better than the j-10c the rafale is a
heavier fighter plane it has much more
thrust
it has a better radar system better
radar capabilities it has a better
weapons package
compared to the j-10c so there's no
comparison between these two uh aircraft
now the pakistanis also use f-16s which
is a 1970s vintage
fighter plane it's still a good fighter
plane but it's an old one
so if you compare the j the j-10c and
the f-16 the f-16 is still
a superior aircraft compared to the
j-10c so why is is pakistan buying this
chinese aircraft which is not that great
it's because they have no other option
when it comes to the f-16 there are lots
of restrictions
to its use
the americans won't allow the child the
pakistanis to use it in certain ways
which kind of ties the pakistani hands
behind their back and behind its back in
some cases
for instance american weapon systems
always have
what's called what is it called it's
called a kill switch
so if you use that weapon system in a
certain way the americans can disable it
remotely
and the pakistanis don't have the
know-how to disable the kill switch
so that's why they are searching for
other alternatives they don't have a
great deal of money so they will have to
buy whatever the chinese offer them and
that is why they are acquiring the j10c
so it will add to the numbers
that they have i think they're acquiring
i don't know 20 30 of these aircraft
maybe
so
it's because they have no other option
that's why they are acquiring the j-10c
it's not a great aircraft
like you have rightfully pointed out
okay
lavia sony says
why is our system failing to counter
terrorism in kashmir
i know that the situation is better than
before
but still many innocent people are dying
for just living there
so you are right the situation is much
better
in recent years compared to
previous years when kashmir was
not doing so well and we were allowing
the indian government
was allowing all kinds of nonsense to
happen there so in recent years the
situation is much better there are no
major terrorist activities
you have all these pakistani terrorists
being eliminated on a routine basis
there are these encounters that happen
from time to time but we know
what is the outcome of all these
encounters and unfortunately sometimes
you have civilian casualties because of
the terrorist activities
so why is our system failing to counter
this
see when somebody is sick
let's let's take this the case of an
individual
who has tuberculosis for instance when a
person has tuberculosis they will have a
fever
and they will have typically
a persistent cough
so how should you treat this disease
should a doctor offer the patient
paracetamol or aspirin for the fever
and a cuff syrup for the cuff
will that solve the problem
no
so you just
if you if you
administer paracetamol or aspirin and a
cough syrup to the patient you are
treating the symptoms
you are merely treating the symptoms but
you are not treating the root cause
which is the tuberculosis bacillus that
is present in this person's body and it
has overwhelmed the immune system
so to
solve the problem and to cure the
patient you have to administer
antibiotics
that can destroy the tuberculosis
bacillus
the bacterium that causes the disease
and that has to be administered for a
certain period of time then you can
solve the problem once and for all
similarly
we are
doing all these anti-terrorist
activities etc in the kashmir region
we are treating the symptoms
what is the root cause
the root cause
is pakistan
terrorism will end in kashmir
when we resolve the pakistan issue
so that's what needs to happen
that is why
terrorism still persists in kashmir from
time to time sporadically
to address the question and to resolve
the problem once and for all we have to
go to the root cause of the problem
and eliminate the root cause of the
terrorism which is the pakistani army
and pakistan
well the pakistani state
so when we do that the problem will be
solved and the people of kashmir will be
able to finally live in peace for the
first time in 70 plus years
does india have the capability the
capacity of developing an anti-nuke
shield program
so when you talk about an anti-nuke
shield you're talking about a missile
defense system so we have acquired the s
400 system but it's a foreign purchase
we have acquired it from the russians
it's an excellent missile defense system
but the question is
is india capable
of developing an
indigenous missile defense system
ballistic missile defense system so when
it comes to cruise missiles those are
not very fast missiles
and once you detect a cruise missile so
detecting and
destroying a cruise missile is the same
thing as detecting and destroying an
enemy aircraft you need radar systems
and you need to monitor your borders
continuously and when you detect a
cruise missile you go and address it the
same way you would addre
the same way you would deal with
an incoming
enemy fighter aircraft but when it comes
to ballistic missiles the entire
technology and our outlook is different
so ballistic missiles are called
ballistic missiles because they have
this parabolic ballistic or
quasi-ballistic trajectory right
and that is the question
so
you all know about the recent
anti-satellite
test that india did
india test tested an anti-satellite
weapon
so what india essentially did was we had
a defunct satellite
in orbit around the earth it was our
satellite in indian satellite
it was in low to medium earth orbit
and we shot a newly developed missile
at that satellite
intercepted it and destroyed it that's
what i needed so what india achieved is
essentially like shooting a bullet with
another bullet that's the level of
precision you need
to
have
an effective anti-satellite weapon and
the technology is exactly the same
as what you will need
to destroy an incoming ballistic missile
it's more or less the same technology
the level of precision is more or less
the same
right because a satellite in earth orbit
it
travels at an extremely high velocity
very high speed
similar to a ballistic missile's speed
so india has demonstrated anti-satellite
capabilities which means that india also
has anti-ballistic missile capabilities
and we already have our own system
uh the p3 air defense system it's a it's
a two two level defense system
it consists of two two different
missiles
one missile will target incoming
ballistic missiles at high altitudes 80
to 100 kilometers i think
and the second layer is a different
missile which will target
incoming missiles at about 40 kilometers
altitude so in case the first missile
fails the second missile will do the job
so it's a double tire two tire system
that we already have in place it has
been tested it works
we don't quite know exactly what the
development status is right now because
we don't want to
publicize it too much
maybe we have a three-tier system or
maybe we have an advanced system that we
are not talking about
i'm just speculating i am not privy to
what's really happening but we have
already
demonstrated the ability to shoot down
incoming ballistic missiles in the 2000s
before 2010
and even after 2010 i think 2012 13 14
we had certain tests of the system
i am not quite sure recently what is
what has been done but obviously we are
developing the technology
further
so we do have the technology
to take down incoming ballistic missiles
nuclear missiles
and maybe maybe it it may possibly be at
an advanced
level of maturity by now because we are
now in the 2020s and
one expects that technology matures
as uh the time goes by so i think we are
in good hands
um
and yeah so india does have the
capacity
of taking down incoming ballistic
missiles with its own technology
do vampires exist or existed or did they
exist in the past
so what's a vampire according to the
standard
standard lore
a vampire is a person who has died and
who has come back from the dead an
undead person
and this person only comes out at night
because the sunlight burns their skin
and they sustain themselves by
preying on living human beings and
drinking their blood
so that is the
the standard definition of vampire from
the brahm bram stoker
school right dracula
and all that so you know what that is
obviously not possible people cannot
come back from the dead
undead people cannot exist it's
biologically not possible from whatever
we know of biology it's simply not
possible
otherwise you would have vampiric
animals as well if such things were
possible so those mythical magical
vampires clearly don't exist okay that
is
simply not there
you have these ancient
tradition the ancient lore
in transylvania et cetera about vampires
well
i think it's just folk tales and all
that there is no evidence that vampires
actually exist
there's another category of empire that
people talk about it's called the
psychic vampire it is certain
individuals who who suck out all the
energy from any room they enter if you
interact with them for some time you
feel all drained and drained of energy
so those are psychic vampires or or
energy vampires so that's also again
kind of pseudoscience but there are some
people who have that effect right
you talk to them and after the
interaction you feel all tired and
drained that person is just too
demanding too
narcissistic too self-centered and too
aggressive
so those people are called energy
vampires or psychic vampires and those
people
we all know some of them
either among our colleagues or friends
or family or whatever you know so
everybody has met such people so those
vampires do exist you know some some
people are like that
okay hq says if genes contribute to a
person's height why are genji indians
taller than their parents despite having
the same genes
and abhishek has answered complain
okay very
interesting question and answer
but this answer does have a grain of
truth in it
so there are two components to how tall
you can be
nature and nurture
nature is the genes
that you carry
there is a certain maximum height that
is programmed into your genetics
so that is the maximum height you can
when a child is born
there is a certain programming in their
genes of the maximum height they can
achieve but they are not guaranteed
to grow that tall
so what makes them grow to a certain
height it's the kind of upbringing and
upbringing they have the kind of diet
they eat and the kind of activity the
level they have
while they are growing
so a child who eats a very nutritious
balanced healthy diet and who also is
very physically active who engages in
sports or athletic activities that child
will grow
and reach
close to the genetic maximum potential
that they have
but a child who doesn't eat a good diet
eats junk food all the time too much
sugar
and is sedentary doesn't engage in
athletic activities etc that child will
not reach its genetic maximum
right so indians have a certain genetic
limit which which most indians have not
reached because in the past in the past
two three in the past thousand years
india's diet was very poor we were under
foreign occupation the british
engineered hundreds of artificial
famines so indians underwent went
through a couple of centuries of near
starvation
after independence india has been a very
poor nation a low income nation a third
world nation
the diet has been very poor so that's
why indians are short today
right but now that india is finally
becoming a reasonably
it's beginning to take its first steps
towards prosperity so the overall diet
is improving and that's why the new kids
the gen z zoomer kids today
you will see that they are typically
taller than their parents
india's genetic maximum is quite high
quite taller than what we see on average
in india today for instance we talk
about the great yamnya invaders of
europe who had indian origins they were
all approximately six feet tall
very very tall strong muscular guys
right
so that is an example of the kind of
genetics you had in india in india in
ancient days recently they found some
some skeletons in up
from 30 40 000 years ago the average
height was about six feet one inches
so that kind of tells you the kind of
genetic uh
programming that our ancestors had and
which which we also carry
so it's all about
the kind of diet you eat as a kid and
the kind of activity levels you have as
a kid if you eat good diets
and if you are physically very active
you gotta get tall taller
otherwise you want that's how it goes
who is david sassoon was it good for
indians david sassoon was a drug dealer
so the history in brief of david sassoon
is that he was a baghdadi jew
he was he was from a prominent jewish
family in baghdad
uh
they think i i think this family was
they were the treasurers of the
of the king or whoever it was in baghdad
and but because of the jews they were
persecuted
so they fled from baghdad they first
went to persia and from persia they came
to india and they settled in mumbai
which was then called bombay
and they were the treasurers of that
region of baghdad so i suppose they
brought with them lots of
plundered wealth
so david sassoon was the patriarch of
this family
because of the all the wealth that he
brought with him from from baghdad he
was able to establish a big business in
india in bombay
he became one of the prominent drug
dealers
under the auspices of the east india
company the drug dealing happened with
china
so uh
even today in shanghai there is this
building which is the name of the
sassoons
so they established a big trading center
in shanghai
right this was part of the of the
chinese century of humiliation so there
was this big competition happening in
china at the time
among indians in the drug deal drug
trade there were at least 23 other
companies all run by parsees
parsees in shanghai at the time
so david sassoon was able to defeat all
of them and he became the biggest drug
dealer
opium trade
in china and that made him fabulously
wealthy it made his family fabulously
wealthy and
they became one of the wealthiest
families in all of asia
and when you are a drug dealer like
pablo escobar or somebody you will do a
lot of charitable work small small
charitable works just to make it look to
the public like you know you're a good
person you're doing you're giving
something back to society
so david sassoon
opened some library in bombay david
sasson library and opened some
synagogues and did some other public
works just to make it look like you know
he's a good guy no one knew what he's
doing in changi
so he was a drug dealer the family's
wealth and fortune came from the drug
trade
later they all emulated out of india
because there's so much money and they
all became part of the british
aristocracy they were
invested with certain titles baronet etc
so that that in short is the story of
david sassoon drug dealer nothing else
was it good for indians
is that even a question he did nothing
for india
okay this is the final question for
today what are your views on kalicharan
kali charon was fantastic he is
fantastic yeah he is fantastic fabulous
fabulous west indies left-handed batsman
brilliant
attacking batsmen
from the 1970s and 1980s that's
one of the very
best west indies bats with
of that time his average was in the mid
40s but he was very good very attacking
very aggressive great player of fast
bowling he took dennis lilly and jeff
thompson to the cleaner several times
see the videos on youtube
so i'm a big fan of alvin kalicharin
that's what i have to say about
kali-chan
all right
gentlemen ladies friends brothers
sisters all of you thank you so much for
all the questions
wonderful talking to all of you
and we will have one more session
tomorrow in which i will take live chat
questions
so
we begin the new year with this session
i wish you all the very best in this new
year
i wish you great success great
prosperity great health
and a lot of happiness thank you very
much for your viewership for your
support
and let's keep going
see you tomorrow take care bye